<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A just and modest vindication of His Royal Highness the Duke of York in observations upon a late revived pamphlet, intituled, A word without doors, wherein the reasons and arguments of that author, are considered and examined.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46377</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1222</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16770</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11859103</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11859103</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49982</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46377)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49982)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 499:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A just and modest vindication of His Royal Highness the Duke of York in observations upon a late revived pamphlet, intituled, A word without doors, wherein the reasons and arguments of that author, are considered and examined.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Benskin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A word without doors concerns the succession of the Duke of York to the throne.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>Word without doors.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49982:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Juſt and Modeſt VINDICATION OF HIS ROYAL HIGHNESS THE Duke of YORK: In Obſervations upon a late Revived Pamphlet, Intituled, <hi>A WORD WITHOUT DOORS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN The Reaſons and Arguments of that AUTHOR, are Conſidered and Examined.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Benskin</hi> in <hi>Green</hi>'s <hi>Rents,</hi> near <hi>Fleetbridge.</hi> M. DC. LXXX.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49982:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49982:2"/>
            <head>Obſervations upon a Pamphlet, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>A Word without Doors,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>IT is now about a Year ſince, I hapned to meet with a Pamphlet, called, <hi>A Word without Doors:</hi> And becauſe I found it very much commended, I read it over, but could not diſcover any thing of ſo great worth, as the World's praiſes gave me cauſe to expect; Thoſe ſtrong Concluſions, thoſe invincible Arguments which the World cried it up for, I confeſs, I could not find out. However, I did not wonder that moſt Men eſteemed it; it is no new thing to Man, to take every little Image, or appearance of an Argument, which tends to prove that which he deſires, for unanſwerable Concluſions. Now the greater part of this Nation, though perhaps not the wiſer, and I think, not at all the honeſter, earneſtly deſire the Excluſion of his ROYAL HIGHNESS, and therefore cannot but approve any thing that ſeems to open them a way to it, by removing not only the difficulty, but the ſeeming injuſtice of the action. This Pamphlet having read, I threw by, where it ſtill had laid, if the reſtleſs temper of evil-minded Men had not revived it to the World againſt the coming of the Parliament, as if they meant thereby to recommend to this Houſe of Commons, the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of that very thing which was, perhaps, the great, if not the Onely Cauſe of the Diſſolution of the other. By this ſober Men will conſider, whether the Author and his Abettors do ſo much deſire a Parliament as they pretend, who are ſo diligent to caſt, I may ſay, a ſtumbling Block in their way, by thruſting them, as it were, upon a Buſineſs, which we have great reaſon to believe they ſhall not only not compaſs, but by the attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, may be, ſhorten their Seſſions, and ſo diſappoint them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49982:3"/>
and the people of ſo many good and glorious things they may do for the benefit and ſatisfaction of all honeſt Men; 'twas for this reaſon that I thought, it might not be amiſs to ſhew the World, That there are no other directions in that adored Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, that do either juſtifie the Bill for Succeſſion, or facilitate the paſſing of it, than there was in every Mans underſtanding before.</p>
            <p>Not to ſpeak any thing of the Author, (for I intend not Reflections) I do believe him a Member of the late Houſe of Commons: For the Matter of his Book, a Man may conſider it under theſe three Heads.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Some Poſitions or Principles on which he builds and from which he derives the very foundation and being of Civil Government.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The juſtneſs and force of his Arguments to prove his main end, viz. <hi>The Lawfulneſs of Diſinheriting a Prince, if the Good of the People require it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, I ſhall obſerve the Examples he alledges how far they make for his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>And now firſt, for his Principles of the Original and Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Government, <hi>pag.</hi> 3. he ſays, <hi>That the inclination of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to live in company did proceed of nature, and ſo of God the Author of nature; and that the juriſdiction of Magiſtrates in general is alſo of God, and ordained by him for the common good of mankind:</hi> But then he adds, <hi>That the particular Forms of Government in this or that manner, to have many, few, or one Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor, or that they ſhould have this or that Authority, more or leſs, for a longer or ſhorter time, or whether ordinarily by Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or by Election, all theſe are ordained and diverſified by the particular poſitive Laws of every Countrey, and are not eſtabliſht by either Law natural or divine, but left by God to every Nation and Countrey, to pitch upon what Form of Government they ſhall think moſt proper to promote the Common Good of the whole, beſt adapted to the natures, conſtitution, and other circumſtances of the</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:49982:3"/>
               <hi>people, which accordingly for the ſame reaſons may be altered or amended in any of its parts, by the mutual conſent of the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors and governed, whenever they ſhall ſee reaſonable cauſe ſo to do.</hi> Thus far our Author. And now what may we conclude from this? That which no Man did ever deny, that Government and Authority is of God, but the ſeveral particular Forms in the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Nations and Countries of the Earth, are of Men, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alterable by them as he ſays well, <hi>By the conſent of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors and governed.</hi> Was there ever any thing more reaſonable than this? or was this ever queſtioned by any man? Surely we all know that the KING, with His Two Houſes, may direct the Succeſſion of the Crown, but their conſents muſt then be had, <hi>that of the Governor, as well as of the governed;</hi> that is, the conſent of the KING, as well as that of His People in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: ſo that all his matter is no more than this, That the Bill for Excluding His ROYAL HIGHNESS is not in itſelf unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, becauſe by poſſibility it may become otherwiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> by gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Royal Aſſent, which we agree; and wiſh men would reſt ſatisfied till that Aſſent be gained, to which it is moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable we ſhould all ſubmit: And indeed when the KING by Act of Parliament ſhall have declared another Succeſſor, I ſhall as readily and willingly obey Him then, as till then I think my ſelf obliged in Duty and Conſcience to adhere to the Right Heir. And what likelihood there is of gaining the Royal Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to ſuch a Bill, (after ſuch repeated Declarations, ſuch large and Royal Proffers from His MAJESTY, as never yet were made by any King to His Parliament, provided always that they diſturb not the Succeſſion and Deſcent of the Crown in the Right Line) or what reaſon men can have to imagine that they may get more, (as ſome men upon baſe and ignoble ends have imagined) is not only not underſtood by me, but I do think the grounds of their hopes as unreaſonable as they are unkind; but not to mention the ſtrange advantages ſome men do conceive from the prevailing preſent neceſſity of His MAJESTIES Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, a matter not fit for our handling, return we to our Author.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:49982:4"/>
As I allow him the particular Forms of Government to be of men, by God's permiſſion, and therefore alterable by them whenſoever they ſhall agree ſo to do: So I truſt it will be granted that thoſe particular Forms, made for the general good, purſuant to the principles of man's nature, and God's intention, become ſo ſacred, that they are not to be touched or invaded by any part of a people under a Government, be it what it will. Now the particular Government of <hi>England</hi> is a ſucceſſive and hereditary Monarchy, directed and maintained by moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Laws, which to alter or deſtroy in any part of it by any number of men, were, by the Laws of the Land, the very higheſt offence, nay, the very attempt or deſign of ſuch a thing, in the judgment of Law worthy the higheſt puniſhments; for as it is true, that by the permiſſion of God ſeveral Nations have pitcht upon ſeveral Governments, ſo it is as true, that when they are once ſetled, be they what they will, they muſt be obeyed and complied with. Now then in <hi>England</hi> the Government is in Kings Hereditarily, who, though they can make no Laws, (there's the peoples happineſs) yet can none be made without them, (there's the Princes Prerogative;) nor can any thing, though paſt both Houſes, without ſuch Aſſent, have the force and effect of a Law. The King's breath, like the Almighties, once quickens and gives life to that which before was but a dead Form; If then the KING be (as I think no man dares queſtion it) our Lawful and Rightful Sovereign, it is no hard matter to find out His Right Heir; who is not, I think, diſabled, by any Law yet in being, to ſucceed for any cauſe whatſoever, unleſs the Heir ſhould prove to be a Natural, and ſo uncapable of governing. If any offence ſhould diſable a Right Heir, ſurely it ſhould be Treaſon; yet though ſuch an Heir were convicted and attainted of Treaſon, if betwixt the Attainder and Execution the King ſhould dye, the Attainder, <hi>ipſo facto eo inſtante,</hi> is reverſed, in judgment of Law, and ſuch would become King <hi>de jure &amp; facto;</hi> ſo that I think we are in this agreed, That a Right Heir to the Crown of <hi>England</hi> may be ſet aſide, <hi>concurrentibus his qui in jure requiruntur,</hi> and thoſe he tells us, <hi>are the Governor and the</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49982:4"/>
               <hi>governed.</hi> There is then a poſſibility of doing it lawfully, there is one way and but one; and as I allow, it were not unlawful if it were ſo done, ſo he muſt allow me, that till that be done, it is and always will be unlawful; and perhaps even after that ſevere; for there are, no doubt, ſeveral very worthy perſons who poſſeſs large Eſtates in Church-lands, which may by Act of Parliament be took from them, yet would they think it hard meaſure if they ſhould; and yet it is ſtrange men ſhould think that hard meaſure and injuſtice, if done to them, which themſelves think moſt fit and reaſonable to offer to others: And ſurely His ROYAL HIGHNESS has every whit as good Right and Title to the Crown, ſhould the KING dye without Iſſue, as thoſe worthy perſons can poſſibly have to their Inheritances: If there be any difference, it is this, That the DUKE's Right is much more ancient than theirs, who can Claim from as many hundred years as they can generations, and much more. I have often obſerved with ſcorn and indignation, the inclination of moſt men to ſpeak evil of Dignities, even ſuch, whoſe deſperate Fortunes render them uncapable of ſuſtaining a loſs, have an ill word for the Duke; make more againſt him, in ſome mens judgments, than all his Perſonal Services, his Quality, Right of Blood, his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Virtues, his Father's Memory and Merit, and a Rightful Title from above 600 years can do for him.</p>
            <p>But come we now to the ſecond thing, the Argument he uſes: And firſt let us obſerve, that the thing he endeavors to prove, is, <hi>That it is lawful to diſinherit a Prince, if the general good of the People require it.</hi> To which I have but two words to ſay; that is, That if he mean, he may be diſinherited by the conſent of KING and People, we have allow'd it before; if he mean otherwiſe, he ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues againſt that which he himſelf has ſet down before as a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, but what, and how far does he extend the word <hi>Prince,</hi> to an Heir apparent only? For it may as well include a Prince Reigning, who by his Rule might be depoſed and removed, when ever the giddy-headed multitude ſhould fanſie it to be for their good; and who ſhall tell them it is not ſo, if they believe it? Who ſhall perſuade, or rather convince the multitude, that they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49982:5"/>
are in the wrong? it were a leſs task to repeat <hi>Hercules</hi> labors: This then is a dangerous Poſition, and may be of infinite ill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence; nor does it excuſe him, to ſay he lays the power in the Governor, that is the King, as well as in the people that are gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and that therefore the King can be in no danger; for the People was ever but too apt to forget the firſt part of his Maxim, and to exerciſe their own power to the prejudice of the Governor; and that this has been practiſed, and in our memory, we have all too great and ſad cauſe to remember. One of his Arguments is, <hi>That the ſame people at different times have had different Forms of Government;</hi> and this is true, but I do not ſee what that makes for him: For if thoſe different Forms of Government were brought in by a full conſent of all perſons concerned, it has been agreed before; if otherwiſe, that ſuch things have been done, is no Argument that they were juſtly and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully done. He does not ſhew that the Authors of ſuch change did well in ſo doing, though God might make uſe of their Evils to work good out of; for if he be pleaſed for the correction of the Prince, or puniſhment of the People, to ſuffer Princes to be removed, and others to be placed in their rooms, either by the Factions of the Nobility, or Rebellion of the People, in all ſuch caſes the judgment of God, who hath power to give and to take away Kingdoms, is moſt juſt; yet the Miniſtry of Men, who execute God's judgments without Commiſſion, is ſinful and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, God doth but turn and uſe Mens unrighteous Acts to the performance of his righteous Decrees. <hi>The Jews,</hi> he ſays, <hi>had once no Kings, and they would have Kings, and had;</hi> What then? Did they do well to alter the Government? No ſurely, though the ſecret purpoſe of God's Eternal Decrees were ſerved and compaſt by that change, yet the deſire of alteration was in them a ſin, and a great one, which no man can doubt that has read <hi>Samuel</hi>'s Story, <hi>Is it not wheat harvest to day, I will call upon the Lord, and he ſhall ſend thunder and rain, that ye may perceive and ſee that your wickedneſs is great which ye have done in the ſight of the Lord, in asking you a King.</hi> And again, the People confeſs in altering the Government they had ſinned, for preſently upon
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49982:5"/>
the Thunder and Rain, they tremble and cry out to <hi>Samuel, That he ſhould pray for his ſervants to the Lord his God that they died not, for they had added unto all their ſins the evil to ask for a King;</hi> ſo that though he makes uſe of their asking a King, as an Argument for his aſſerting the Lawfulneſs of altering Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments when the People require it, I do think that God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf declares that it was a ſin in them, and yet they thought they did for the beſt, and that the general good of all; it is plain they did it for that reaſon, and offer it for their reaſon to <hi>Samuel</hi> of their requeſt, for it was that they might have one to judge them, like other Nations, that he might go before them, and fight their Battels; that is, defend and ſave them from their Enemies, to whom the old age of <hi>Samuel,</hi> and the ill government of his Sons expoſed them ſo often. When then may a people expect to change a Government lawfully, if the <hi>Jews</hi> in this caſe did not? Surely if ever an alteration by a people might be juſtified or excuſed, it ſhould be here, where they deſired to bring in a Government which had before been determined, in the ſecret Counſel of the Almighty, they ſhould one day have, and which for ſpecial reaſons and purpoſes muſt of neceſſity have been one day impoſed upon them; yet becauſe their intention was not to ſerve God's great and hidden purpoſe, but their own inclinations, it was criminal in them, but in their next generation, a juſt duty to own and obey that power their Fathers had wickedly intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced; for when a people innovate in the Government they do ill, but the next generation may and ought to continue it, as well for that they know no other, as for that to diſcontinue it, were in them another Innovation. What has been ſaid of the <hi>Jews,</hi> is true of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and all other Nations; God often permitted them to alter the Government, but it does not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore follow, that it was lawful ſo to do, though our Author ſeems to juſtifie them, becauſe they proſper'd in it, which is a ſtrange argument; I was yet to learn, that matter of Fact was an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument or proof of matter of right, that is to ſay, that the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful event of things was to be the rule and meaſure of our judgments, as to the equity and juſtice of them, true it is, the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49982:6"/>
world judges ſo; but the wiſe, learned and honeſt, have ever exploded it, and ſurely with great reaſon: For what a world ſhould we ſoon have, if it were once granted that a thing is lawfully done, becauſe luckily effected; at that rate, he that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led himſelf a Dog, as deſerving that name, (if he could be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of thoſe Evils the Prophet told him he ſhould do, and which he trembled to hear) might have triumph'd after the execution of them. <hi>Ahab</hi> too was ſurely an honeſt man, and had good right to the Vineyard becauſe he got it; ſurely if our Author had well conſider'd the conſequence of this Argument, he would have left it out; he has forgot, no doubt, it was the very Argument made uſe of within the memory of man, by a number of as great Villains as ever lived on Earth, for the juſtifying of as great a wickedneſs, as ſaving one, ſtory ever told or people heard of: But let us now look upon the Examples he cites, and the Reader will then find I do not wrong him, in charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him with the laſt Argument. His firſt Example is <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> who being diſpleaſed with the King, with five ſixth parts of the people ſet up a new Kingdom; indeed he has been ſo kind to ſet down the anſwer to it, it was by particular approbation from God: <hi>Reluru every man to his houſe, for this thing is of me, ſaith the Lord.</hi> It was lawful till then for <hi>Rehoboam</hi> to raiſe an Army for the reducing the Rebel to his duty, but after ſuch a declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it had been the higheſt impudence, folly and impiety to have thought of it. If the late Tyrant that made ſuch a noiſe in the world, could have ſhewed the ſame warrant, how unjuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiable had then been all the honeſt and dutiful Endeavors of ſo many loyal and ſaithful Subjects for his ruine. It was never doubted ſure, but that the Will of God over-rules and juſtifies the Acts he wills<hi>:</hi> without ſuch a command it had been a ſin in <hi>Jehu</hi> to kill his King, the Royal Strumpet knew ſo much, and could tell him ſo, <hi>Had</hi> Zimri <hi>peace that ſlew his Maſter?</hi> No, but he alone that commanded the Fact could juſtifie it; I do think therefore our Author concludes ill in his 5th page, <hi>That ſince God did permit and allow this in his own Commonwealth, (which,</hi> he ſays, <hi>was to be a pattern for all others) no doubt he</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:49982:6"/>
               <hi>will approve the ſame in other Kingdoms, whenever his ſervice and glory, or the happineſs of the Weal Publick ſhall require.</hi> Is not this to argue <hi>à particulari ad generale?</hi> becauſe once God for ſpecial Reaſons permitted a Rebellion, which without his Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to have approv'd it, had been a ſin for <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and all his Followers to continue it; therefore without any ſuch evidence of his good liking, no doubt for the future, in other Kingdoms, the like may be practiſed, if the people ſhall judge God's glory and their own good to require it, that is the plain and neceſſary inference of his Argument.</p>
            <p>The next Example, is that of the Children of <hi>Don Alonzo,</hi> Prince of <hi>Spain,</hi> who, after their Father's death, were ſet aſide, by conſent of the States, and the King their Grandfather, for their great Uncle; but this is no more than before is granted, that the King and Parliament may declare and appoint a Succeſſor.</p>
            <p>The third is of <hi>Hugh Capel,</hi> choſen to the prejudice of <hi>Charles,</hi> which no doubt was an injurious Act, though done in a full Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of the States, and though he ſeemed to have forſaken them, by forſaking the virtues and cuſtoms of his Countrey, to adhere to its ancient Enemies the <hi>Germans,</hi> yet the compariſon thoſe States made of themſelves to a Pilot, is not according to the wiſdom of ſo great an Aſſembly; for though Men ought to get an able Pilot, yet if the Maſter of the Veſſel be not ſuch in your eſteem, they ought not to thruſt him out for another, without compounding with him for the right he has to the Veſſel; and what compoſition ſhall be given to a Prince? what ſhall be given him in lieu of a Kingdom?</p>
            <p>Our Author is now come to Home-Preſidents, which will be the clearer, becauſe we ſuppoſe our Countreymen to be better read in their own Story.</p>
            <p>The firſt is the 2d Son of the Conqueror, getting the Crown by Aſſent of Parliament, his elder Brother being then buſie at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and 'twas indeed a pretty return for a Chriſtian State to rob a Prince of his Right, becauſe he was expoſing his life to enlarge the bounds, and to increaſe the glory of <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> a very excellent Preſident.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:49982:7"/>
Next, He cites <hi>Henry</hi> the younger Brother, who having no right, God did ſo proſperhim as to beat his eldeſt Brother, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he concludes it was lawful to diſinherit him; God ſuffer'd him to pull out his eyes too, but I dare not therefore believe he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved the cruelty.</p>
            <p>Another he brings, of receiving <hi>Stephen</hi> to the prejudice of <hi>Henry</hi> the 2d of that name, but that, it ſeems, thrived not ſo well; ſurely God gave viſible proof of his diſliking it, ſince he ſuffer'd it to be a means to well nigh ruine the Kingdom, which was at laſt preſerved by a Parliament, reſtoring all to right, and declaring young <hi>Henry</hi> Succeſſor, which <hi>Stephen</hi> was forced to join in to the Excluſion of his Son; and had it not been better never to have wrong'd him, than for your own ſakes to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to do him right? And theſe are our Author's Examples, which how much they make for his purpoſe, whether they are of ſufficient authority to determine ſo great and ſo important a matter as a Right to a Crown, I leave to the judgment of every impartial Reader.</p>
            <p>The thing he firſt deſires to have granted, is the lawfulneſs of altering Government by the King, Lords and Commons, and that was never a queſtion as I know, or have heard; yet whether ignorantly, or deſignedly, I know not. He mentions no Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, ſave that of the <hi>Spaniard</hi> onely to that purpoſe, the reſt, are ill Preſidents of Princes injuriouſly and cauſleſly diſinherited by the States onely, and not by King and States, out of which a reflecting ſpirit might conclude, That though he colour his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign with the ſpecious title of King, Lords and Commons, yet that he would gladly perſuade the people that they alone may do it, becauſe by many ill Examples it appears they have done ſo; and this we might have more reaſon to believe, for that in his 8th page he ſays, <hi>Thus did the Parliament diſpoſe of the Crown in thoſe days;</hi> ſo that the authority and aſſent of the King is but for faſhion-ſake.</p>
            <p>Now though it appears that either he has ſet down a Maxim never queſtioned, and therefore not to be proved, in laying ſuch power in the King and His two Houſes, or elſe diſguiſed another,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49982:7"/>
which with all his Examples he has not made out, ſo that I might very well end here; I yet do think it not amiſs to ſet down ſome Examples of as good Authority I am ſure, and nothing leſs to the purpoſe of the other ſide, to prove, <hi>That how though a people ſtir and torment themſelves never ſo much, God, who neither can do, nor will ſuffer wrong, has ſtill brought things about, and either made right take place again, or if for hidden cauſes he has ſuffer'd them for a time, has yet at laſt, by heavy judgments, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced the world, that he does not approve all that he permits, and that he will ſurely be avenged on them, who injure even the Divine Majeſty, by ſtamping their own wicked deeds with a pretended appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation from Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Begin we with the greateſt Man that perhaps ever lived, <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caeſar,</hi> one, to whom the State was as much bound to as any man; one attended with continual and wonderful ſucceſs whil'ſt he obey'd the Government he was born under; no ſooner had he alter'd that, ſcarce warm in his ill gotten Empire, while he was yet imagining thoſe vaſt Enterpriſes of compaſſing the world with his Armies, met the reward of his unjuſtice in that very place, and from thoſe very men where and with whom he had all the reaſon in the world to think himſelf moſt ſecure.</p>
            <p>If ever people had or could have cauſe to remove a Prince, ſure the <hi>Romans</hi> might have done <hi>Nero,</hi> yet what vengeance follow'd him that ſerv'd them in it <hi>Galba,</hi> how ſad and ſudden was his deſtruction, the Hiſtories of that great people do ſufficiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us. Innumerable are the Examples abroad, but let us ſee at home.</p>
            <p>The Conqueror himſelf, though he died poſſeſt of the Crown which he had won, was yet, for the many alterations he made in the Church and State, ſo perplext at his death, and had ſo ſtrange a ſenſe of it, that he durſt not bequeath it to any of his children, believing that divine vengeance would follow them for his Crimes, and ſo it did, as we ſhall ſhew anon; and yet who, if a Conqueror may not, who then ſhall venture upon Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? His Sons, for the wrong done to <hi>Robert</hi> their elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or rather <hi>Henry,</hi> for <hi>William</hi> had it from his Father, eſcaped
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49982:8"/>
not juſtice from Heaven, and dyed a violent death. And no leſs evident was that juſtice, when a King muſt diſinherit his own beloved Son, and join with a Parliament, to acknowledge and pay a young Boy his Right, to which natural affection and thirſt of Empire muſt give way.</p>
            <p>The Parliament, at the requeſt of <hi>Henry</hi> afterwards the 4th of that name, depoſed <hi>Richard</hi> the 2d, and what was <hi>Henry</hi>'s and that Kingdoms reward, a life in continual jeopardy, always fearing, always troubled, continually in War, Rebellions great and frequent, that ſhook the very Crown of his Head? and by whom did Heaven do this? by thoſe very men who had lifted him to the top of his ambition and power, with the forfeiture of their duty and conſcience, making them alſo to periſh in the action, giving them the reward of Traytors for their firſt villany: But ere we leave this Prince, I ſhall obſerve what opinion he himſelf had of his Right, though he had an Act of Parliament joined with his nearneſs of blood for't, however living he carried it, at the approach of death he begins to queſtion whether he had done well, that is, whether the people of <hi>England</hi> could remove his Couſin, and give him the Crown, and owns his juſt doubt to his Son with grief, and no doubt with much concern and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity of mind. Now though he dyed in his Bed, and his Son after him, yet was his Sons life ſhort, the firſt part filled with follies, and the latter with troubles, in the very entrance upon the Throne hardly eſcaping a violent death, which however reacht his Son after him, who was the viſible unfortunate Object of God's juſtice, for the ſins of his Grandfather, for being full of virtue, goodneſs and piety, we cannot imagine his own ſins pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on his head ſo many judgments, a long and miſerable life, deſpiſed and neglected at home, conquer'd and thruſt out of all abroad, ſtill in War, becauſe he loved Peace; always a loſer, in every thing unfortunate; and thoſe loſſes coming upon him by degrees, till from one to another, like <hi>Job</hi>'s calamities, the laſt (ſave his own) was the loſs of his Sons life, more than once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, twice impriſoned, and at laſt murdered.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49982:8"/>
The Parliament impowered <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th to appoint a Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor by will, if he had no Iſſue by his third Wife; by the ſame power his two Daughters were diſinherited; yet God in due time made way for both; and what was the end of thoſe men, who by a Will of <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th, would have ſet them aſide? yet had they much colour for ſo doing; for they had been ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready by Act of Parliament paſt 228. of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th, which Act was indeed repealed by a ſubſequent 35 of the ſame King; but the latter Act was full of Proviſo's, Conditions and Limitations, and the Intereſt and Eſtate of the two Princeſſes in the Crown, made ſubject to the laſt Will of that King, or his Letters Patents; add to this, that the colourable pretence of ſaving Religion, which ſame, to neceſſitate their actions, and therefore if it not juſtifie, might at leaſt help to palliate and excuſe them. Their end was vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent: <hi>Northumberland</hi> and his Party fell by the Sword, becauſe they would not know and follow the waies of Peace and Right; and what was unhappy, though moſt juſt with them, periſht the Lady <hi>Jane Grey,</hi> and her Husband, who had no other fault, but that of too great an obedience to their Father's wills and pleaſures; and in the puniſhment of that moſt excellent Princeſs, ſurely God taught the world, that not even the glorious pretence of Religion (which muſt needs, and did periſh, when the right Heir gotten) though ſtrengthened by a diſinheriting Act of Parliament, and the Will of a juſt departed Monarch could juſtifie their Rebellion: Many more preſidents I could cite, but I ſhall conclude with this one, the Reſtauration of our preſent Soveraign, which by how much more it was the wonderful effect of an immediate provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, not aſſiſted by the arm of fleſh; ſo much more it is remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to prove our purpoſe, and our poſition which we laid down a little before, <hi>That whatever a people may do, God will do juſtice and right to them that ſuffer wrong.</hi> The latter part of our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's Book, being an Anſwer to a Pamplet I never ſaw, I can ſay nothing to; and now if we muſt end, we will do it with a line of his own Book, which he ſets down as a falſe, but we as a true Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, <hi>That Monarchy is of Divine Right; and that Princes in</hi> England <hi>ſucceed by nature and generation only, and not by authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:49982:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>admiſſion or approbation of the people.</hi> For further Information I refer the Reader to Sir <hi>Robert Philmer</hi>'s Political Diſcourſes: And now before I conclude, I would have no man to think that I do in all this deſign, to leſſen or diſparage the Authority of a Parliament: I have for thoſe two Houſes the higheſt venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion imaginable, and own them joyned with Majeſty, to be my lawful Governours: Nor would I have any man believe that I ether profeſs or affect the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Catholick Religion: There's no man does more ardently deſire to ſee the ſame Religion now eſtabliſht by Law, continued and ſecured to us and our poſterity together, with the King's Perſon, and the eſtabliſht Government, than my ſelf; and it is that which will be worthy of the cares and pains of a Parliament, to provide for by the moſt effectual means, alwaies provided they be ſuch as may neither diſparage the grave wiſdom, nor ſwerve from the High Juſtice of that great and Auguſt Aſſembly; for ſurely a good end muſt be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt by like means, elſe all is naught, there being nothing more ſure than that the unlawful means corrupt and deſtroy that good end which they lead to; and this is that which a Parliament may, and I hope, will look to when they ſit, which no doubt they had long ſince done, if by the unreaſonable malice of ſome, and miſtaken meaſures of others, fears and jealouſies had not been carried and fomented to that degree, that the intereſt of our King and his People ſeemed not to be the ſame it ever was, and I truſt ever ſhall be a good underſtanding betwixt both: Which that it may be increas'd, and for ever continue, ought to be the prayer of every good Engliſh man.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
